{"tossups": [{"question": "This leader\u2019s cause was damaged by constant feuds with Li Zongren over control of the army. This man was forced to form the Second United Front with his enemies after he was kidnapped in the Xi\u2019an [shee-ahn] incident. This man\u2019s wife, Soong Mei-Ling, tried to promote the \u201cfour virtues\u201d during the New Life Movement. For ten points, name this successor of Sun Yat-sen, a Kuomintang leader who set up his base in Taiwan after losing the Chinese Civil War.", "answer": "<b> Chiang</b> Kai-Shek (accept<b> Jiang</b> Jieshi)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Authors like William Simms and Caroline Hentz wrote works in a genre named for their opposition to this novel. The title character of this novel was inspired by Josiah Henson, who wrote two autobiographies detailing his life after he fled to Canada. Many southerners rebutted this novel by claiming it misrepresented friendly relationships between masters and slaves. For ten points, name this 1852 novel by Harriet Beecher Stowe.", "answer": "<b> Uncle Tom\u2019s Cabin</b>, or Life Among the Lowly", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Misc Literature"}, {}, {"question": "The command to conduct this event was allegedly caught on audio tape by Terry Strubbe. This event, which may have been caused by people throwing rocks at a patrolman\u2019s Jeep, was witnessed by John Filo, who took a photograph of Mary Ann Vecchio kneeling next to Jeffrey Miller\u2019s body. The President\u2019s Commission on Campus Unrest was created in the wake of, for ten points, what tragedy in which the Ohio National Guard opened fire on Vietnam War protesters?", "answer": "<b> Kent State</b> shootings", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "At one battle, this ruler urged his men never to \u201close sight of my panache\u201d and noted that they were\u201con the road to honor and victory.\u201d This man, who defeated the Duke of Mayenne at Ivry, was killed by Fran\u00b8cois Ravaillac. The Guise faction in the French Wars of Religion was opposed by this king, who protected Protestant rights by proclaiming the Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this first Bourbon king of France who was a Huguenot before he converted to Catholicism, declaring \u201cParis is well worth a mass.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Henry IV</b> of France (accept<b> Henry</b> III<b> of Navarre</b>; prompt on \u201cHenry;\u201d do not accept or prompt on \u201cHenry III\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A thinker from this country wrote<em> Dialectical and Historical Materialism</em>, which laid the groundwork for this country\u2019s political ideology. In the book<em> Our Revolution</em>, another thinker from this country argued against another thinker from here with the idea of a \u201cpermanent revolution.\u201d One early leader of this country outlined his political philosophy in the \u201cApril Theses.\u201d For ten points, name this former country, whose political thinkers included Leon Trotsky, Joseph Stalin, and Vladmir Lenin.", "answer": "<b> Soviet Union</b> (or<b> USSR</b>; or<b> Union of Soviet Socialist Republics</b>; accept<b> CCCP</b> or<b> Soyuz Sovetskikh Sotsialisticheskikh Respublik</b>; prompt on Russia; prompt on Georgia; prompt on Ukraine) (7) In a publicity stunt, Andrew Carnegie led an elephant across this city\u2019s Eads Bridge to prove the stability of the steel used in its construction. This city\u2019s Forest Park hosted the 1904 World\u2019s Fair. A national park in this city, which was formerly called the Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, contains a massive steel catenary designed by Eero Saarinen. The Gateway Arch is in, for ten points, what large city in eastern Missouri? ANSWER:<b> St. Louis</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A commander in this battle claimed that out of control Ho-Chunk allies started the attack. Despite being shot in the head and both thighs in this battle, Spier Spencer continued to command his Yellow Jackets. The victorious general in this battle succeeded in destroying Prophetstown and, twenty-nine years later, used his fame from this battle to win the Election of 1840. Shawnee forces were defeated in Indiana in, for ten points, what 1811 battle that gave William Henry Harrison a nickname used in his campaign with \u201cTyler, too\u201d?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Tippecanoe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these events divided its participants into \u201cnew\u201d and \u201cold\u201d lights based on their fervor. Another of these events led Charles Finney to describe western New York as the \u201cburned over district.\u201d Samuel Davies was a leader of one of these events, during which humanity was compared to a spider hanging over a fire in the \u201cSinners in the Hands of an Angry God\u201d sermon of Jonathan Edwards. For ten points, name these periods of American Christian religious revival.", "answer": "First and/or Second<b> Great Awakening</b>s (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This man claimed that he drew from the general theory of relativity to create a new religion called Universalism. This man came to power after a foreign power invaded in Operation Weserub\u00a8ung, which enabled him to succeed Johan Nygaardsvold after King Haakon VII fled the country. In 1945, this founder of the Nasjonal Samling party was executed outside Akershus fortress for his collaboration with the Nazis. For ten points, name this treasonous president of Norway.", "answer": "Vidkun<b> Quisling</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "An inscription found at Jarrow claims that this structure\u2019s namesake built it due to \u201cdivine instruction.\u201d The Stanegate was a road that followed a similar path to this structure, which contains a ditch once named after Agricola. Along the North Sea, this structure terminates at Solway Firth. This 73 mile long structure was intended to keep the Picts and other Celtic groups out of Roman territory. A cousin of Trajan names, for ten points, what wall in northern England?", "answer": "<b> Hadrian\u2019s Wall</b> (accept<b> Vallum Aelium</b>)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "George Bancroft\u2019s recommendation of this man was unanimously accepted, ending a debate between Lewis Cass and Martin Van Buren. This president\u2019s administration was able to work with Richard Pakenham to resolve a border dispute, despite this man\u2019s support of the slogan \u201c54-40 or fight.\u201d This president gained Southern support by replacing the infamous \u201cBlack\u201d Tariff with the Walker Tariff. For ten points, name this 11th president, a believer in manifest destiny who oversaw the Mexican-American War.", "answer": "James Knox<b> Polk</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This initiative was brought into effect by the Berlin Decree and subsequently escalated by the Orders in Council, which prompted Scandinavian nations to form the Second League of Armed Neutrality. Following the Battle of Friedland and the signing of the Treaty of Tilsit, one nation joined this initiative; however, that nation later deserted this system, prompting a French invasion of Russia. For ten points, name this Napoleonic system that attempted to impose an economic blockade on Great Britain.", "answer": "<b> Continental System</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Portugalâ€™s refusal to join the Continental System ultimately led to this war in 1808. It included the Battle of Salamanca.", "answer": "<b> Peninsular</b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A decade of turmoil in this country was ushered in with the July Apostasy by king Constantine II. After several weak civilian governments, the Regime of the Colonels took over and ruled this country from 1967 to 1974; when civilian rule was restored, PASOK and New Democracy dominated this country\u2019s politics until the rise of Syriza in the wake of the debt crisis of the early 2010s. For ten points, name this country where Alexis Tsipras was replaced as Prime Minister in 2019.", "answer": "<b> Greece</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "His reforms to church liturgy included a larger use of plainchant.", "answer": "<b> Alfred</b> the Great BONUS:<em> Pastoral Care</em>, the oldest known book in English, is a translation of a work by this \u201cgreat\u201d pope, who sent a mission to England in 596. His reforms to church liturgy included a larger use of plainchant. ANSWER:<b> Gregory</b> I (accept Saint<b> Gregory</b> the Great; accept<b> Gregorian</b> chant) <b></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>Three members of this family received the Legion of Honor in 1909, including Katharine, who worked as a publicist during their tour of Europe. This family produced the Van Cleve</b> <b>catalog from their home base in Dayton, Ohio, where they operated a (+)</b> <b>bicycle shop.</b> <b>Two members of this family added a three-axis control system to a (*)</b> \u201cFlyer\u201d that they tested near Kitty Hawk, North Carolina. For ten points, name this family of engineers that included siblings Katharine, Wilbur, and Orville.", "answer": "<b> Wright</b> family (accept Katharine, Wilbur, and/or Orville<b> Wright</b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this opulent, early-twentieth-century art movement that focused on bold, geometric designs, characterized by the Chrysler Building.", "answer": "Art<b> Deco</b> (accept<b> Style Moderne</b>; accept<b> Zigzag</b> or<b> Streamline</b> Moderne or<b> Moderne </b>until mentioned)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "<b>This country was the site of Operation Dragon Rouge, where foreign special forces had to be deployed to rescue hostages during the Simba Uprising. A crisis in this country was</b> <b>almost mediated by UN Secretary-General Dag (+)</b> <b>Hammarskjold [\u201chammer\u201d-sk\u2019yold],</b> <b>who died in a plane crash in Northern Rhodesia en route to a peace conference. The (*) </b>Katanga Crisis took place in this country, where Joseph Kasa-Vubu was replaced by a man who briefly renamed this country Zaire. For ten points, name this African country where Mobutu Sese Seko led from Kinshasa.", "answer": "<b> Democratic Republic of the Congo</b> (accept<b> DRC</b>; accept<b> Congo-Kinshasa</b>; prompt on\u201cCongo;\u201d do not accept or prompt on \u201cRepublic of the Congo\u201d) (6) <b>This speech attacks a governor whose \u201clips [drip] with the words of interposition and</b> <b>nullification.\u201d The writer of this speech claims to have received a check from America that was marked (+) \u201cinsufficient funds\u201d but goes on to describe former slaves and slaveowners sitting together at the \u201ctable of brotherhood.\u201d The hope that future generations \u201cwill not be (*)</b> judged by the color of their skin but by the content of their character\u201d is proclaimed in, for ten points, what speech given at the 1963 March on Washington by Martin Luther King, Jr.? ANSWER:<b> I Have a Dream</b> speech (prompt on descriptive answers of Martin Luther King\u2019s speech at the March on Washington)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>In this country, student Benno Ohnesorg was killed during a protest against the Shah of Iran. This country was the subject of a declaration by French foreign minister Robert Schuman that paved the way for the European (+) Coal and Steel Community. An economic miracle in this country began under Konrad Adenauer, and it adopted the policy of (*)</b>\u201costpolitik\u201d under Willy Brandt to ease tensions with its neighbor. For ten points, name this former country with capital Bonn that was re-unified with its eastern neighbor in 1990.", "answer": "<b> West Germany</b> (prompt on Germany)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}